What started as a platform for hobbyists
ما بدأ كقاعدة للهواة
is poised to become a multibillion-dollar industry.
يقف اليوم ليصبح صناعة تبلغ عدة مليارات من الدولارات.
Inspection, environmental monitoring, photography and film and journalism:
فأعمال التفتيش ومراقبة البيئة والتصوير وصناعة الأفلام و الصحافة:
these are some of the potential applications for commercial drones,
هي بعض التطبيقات الممكنة للطائرات التجارية المسيرة (بلا طيار)،
and their enablers are the capabilities being developed
وما يدعمها هو قيام منشآت بحوث حول العالم
at research facilities around the world.
بتطوير إمكاناتها.
For example, before aerial package delivery
على سبيل المثال، قبل أن يدخل تسليم الطرود جواً
entered our social consciousness,
إلى وعينا الاجتماعي،
an autonomous fleet of flying machines built a six-meter-tall tower
قام أسطول مستقل من الآلات الطائرة ببناء برج بارتفاع ستة أمتار
composed of 1,500 bricks
مكون من 1500 قطعة آجر
in front of a live audience at the FRAC Centre in France,
أمام متفرجين في مركز "فراك' في فرنسا
and several years ago, they started to fly with ropes.
و قبل بضع سنوات بدأت تطير بالحبال.
By tethering flying machines,
وبربط الآلات الطائرة،
they can achieve high speeds and accelerations in very tight spaces.
يمكنها الوصول إلى سرعات وتسارعات عالية في أماكن ضيقة جداً،
They can also autonomously build tensile structures.
ويمكنها كذلك بناء هياكل مرنة بشكل مستقل
Skills learned include how to carry loads,
و تشمل الخبرة المكتسبة كيفية حمل الأوزان،
how to cope with disturbances,
وكيفية التعامل مع الاضطرابات
and in general, how to interact with the physical world.
و بشكل عام، كيفية التفاعل مع العالم الملموس.
Today we want to show you some new projects that we've been working on.
اليوم نريد أن نريكم بعض المشاريع التي نعمل عليها.
Their aim is to push the boundary of what can be achieved
و هدفها توسيع حدود ما يمكن الوصول إليه
with autonomous flight.
بالطيران المستقل.
Now, for a system to function autonomously,
و هكذا بالنسبة إلى نظام يعمل مستقلاً،
it must collectively know the location of its mobile objects in space.
يجب أن يعرف بالإجمال موقع قطعه المتحركة في الفضاء.
Back at our lab at ETH Zurich,
هناك في مختبرنا في جامعة إي تي إتش في زيوريخ،
we often use external cameras to locate objects,
غالبا ما نستخدم كاميرات خارجية لتحديد مواقع الأشياء
which then allows us to focus our efforts
مما يسمح لنا بتركيز جهودنا
on the rapid development of highly dynamic tasks.
على التطوير السريع للمهمات الديناميكية جداً.
For the demos you will see today, however,
لكن في العروض التي سترونها اليوم
we will use new localization technology developed by Verity Studios,
سنستخدم تقنيات تحديد الموقع التي طورتها ستوديوهات (فيريتي ستوديوز)
a spin-off from our lab.
وهي شركة منبثقة عن مختبراتنا.
There are no external cameras.
لا توجد هنا كاميرات خارجية.
Each flying machine uses onboard sensors to determine its location in space
كل آلة طائرة تستخدم أجهزة استشعار ذاتية لتحدد موقعها في الفضاء
and onboard computation to determine what its actions should be.
و حسابات ذاتية لتحدد ما يجب القيام به.
The only external commands are high-level ones
الأوامر الخارجية الوحيدة هي الأوامر الهامة
such as "take off" and "land."
مثل "أقلع" و "اهبط".
This is a so-called tail-sitter.
و هذه هي مايسمى الجالسة على ذيلها.
It's an aircraft that tries to have its cake and eat it.
إنها طائرة تحاول الاستحواذ على الكعكة وأكلها.
Like other fixed-wing aircraft, it is efficient in forward flight,
ومثل أي طائرة ذات جناح ثابت فهي كفوءة في الطيران إلى الأمام
much more so than helicopters and variations thereof.
أكثر من الطائرات المروحية وأنواعها الأخرى
Unlike most other fixed-wing aircraft, however,
ولكنها خلافاً لمعظم الطائرات الثابتة الجناح
it is capable of hovering,
فهي قادرة على التحويم
which has huge advantages for takeoff, landing
وهذا له فوائد كبيرة في الإقلاع والهبوط
and general versatility.
والاستخدامات العامة.
There is no free lunch, unfortunately.
لسوء الحظ لا يوجد شيء مجاني.
One of the limitations with tail-sitters
أحد عيوب الطائرة الجالسة على ذيلها
is that they're susceptible to disturbances such as wind gusts.
هو أنها عرضة لاضطرابات مثل هبات الريح.
We're developing new control architectures and algorithms
إننا نطور حالياً تصاميم تحكم وخوارزميات
that address this limitation.
لمعالجة هذه العيوب.
The idea is for the aircraft to recover
إن الفكرة هي أن تستعيد الطائرة وضعها
no matter what state it finds itself in,
بغض النظر عن الوضع الذي تجد نفسها فيه.
and through practice, improve its performance over time.
ومن خلال التجربة سيتطور أداؤها مع الوقت.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
OK.
حسناً.
When doing research,
عندما نقوم بالبحوث،
we often ask ourselves fundamental abstract questions
غالبا ما نسأل أنفسنا أسئلة أساسية مجردة
that try to get at the heart of a matter.
تحاول الوصول إلى لب الموضوع.
For example, one such question would be,
وعلى سبيل المثال قد يكون أحد هذه الأسئلة،
what is the minimum number of moving parts needed for controlled flight?
ما هو العدد الأدنى للأجزاء المتحركة المطلوبة للطيران الخاضع للتحكم؟
Now, there are practical reasons
الآن. هناك أسباب عملية
why you may want to know the answer to such a question.
للرغبة في معرفة إجابة هذا السؤال.
Helicopters, for example,
المروحيات مثلاً،
are affectionately known as machines with a thousand moving parts
معروفة بشكل كبير على أنها آلات بآلاف القطع المتحركة
all conspiring to do you bodily harm.
تتعاون جميعها لتعطيك ضرراً جسدياً.
It turns out that decades ago,
اتضح منذ عقود ،
skilled pilots were able to fly remote-controlled aircraft
أن الطيارين ذوو الخبرة كانوا يستطيعون قيادة طائرات التحكم عن بعد
that had only two moving parts:
التي كان لها جزءان متحركان فقط:
a propeller and a tail rudder.
هما المروحة و دفة التوجيه.
We recently discovered that it could be done with just one.
لكننا اكتشفنا مؤخراً إمكانية القيام بذلك بقطعة واحدة فقط.
This is the monospinner,
إنه الدوّار المنفرد،
the world's mechanically simplest controllable flying machine,
وهو الآلة الطائرة القابلة للسيطرة الأبسط ميكانيكياً في العالم،
invented just a few months ago.
التي تم اختراعها فقط قبل أشهر.
It has only one moving part, a propeller.
ولها جزء متحرك واحد فقط هو المروحة.
It has no flaps, no hinges, no ailerons,
وليس لها أي قلابات ولا مفاصل ولا دفات تدوير،
no other actuators, no other control surfaces,
كما أنه ليس لها محركات ولا سطوح للسيطرة،
just a simple propeller.
فقط مروحة بسيطة.
Even though it's mechanically simple,
ومع أنها بسيطة ميكانيكياً،
there's a lot going on in its little electronic brain
إلا أنه يحدث الكثير بعقلها الالكتروني الصغير
to allow it to fly in a stable fashion and to move anywhere it wants in space.
ليسمح لها بالطيران بشكل مستقر وللحركة أينما تريد في الفضاء.
Even so, it doesn't yet have
ومع ذلك، فليس لديها
the sophisticated algorithms of the tail-sitter,
الخوارزمية المعقدة للجالسة على ذيلها،
which means that in order to get it to fly,
ما يعني أنه لجعلها تطير.
I have to throw it just right.
ينبغي علي رميها بالشكل الصحيح
And because the probability of me throwing it just right is very low,
وبما أن احتمال أن تكون رميتي صحيحة هو احتمال ضعيف،
given everybody watching me,
خاصةً أن الجميع يراقبني،
what we're going to do instead
فما سنقوم بفعله بدلا ًعن ذلك
is show you a video that we shot last night.
هو أن نريكم مقطع فيديو صورناه مساء أمس.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
If the monospinner is an exercise in frugality,
وإذا كان الدوار المنفرد تطبيقاً اقتصادياً
this machine here, the omnicopter, with its eight propellers,
فإن هذه الآلة هنا، متعددة الدوارات، بمحركاتها الثمانية ،
is an exercise in excess.
هي تطبيق مغالى فيه.
What can you do with all this surplus?
ماذا تستطيع أن تفعل بكل هذا الفائض؟
The thing to notice is that it is highly symmetric.
ما يمكن ملاحظته أنها متماثلة بشكل كبير.
As a result, it is ambivalent to orientation.
وكنتيجة لذلك فهي لا تتأثربالتيار،
This gives it an extraordinary capability.
وهذا يعطيها إمكانيات غير طبيعية ،
It can move anywhere it wants in space
فيمكنها التحرك إلى أينما تريد في الفضاء
irrespective of where it is facing
بغض النظر عن وجهتها
and even of how it is rotating.
وحتى عن كيفية دورانها.
It has its own complexities,
إن لها تعقيداتها الخاصة،
mainly having to do with the interacting flows
خاصة ما يتعلق بالتيارات المتضاربة
from its eight propellers.
من مراوحها الثمانية.
Some of this can be modeled, while the rest can be learned on the fly.
بعضها يمكن وضع نموذج لها بينما نتعلم الباقي خلال الطيران
Let's take a look.
لنلقِ نظرة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
If flying machines are going to enter part of our daily lives,
إذا كانت الآلات الطائرة ستدخل جزءاً من حياتنا اليومية،
they will need to become extremely safe and reliable.
فعليها أن تكون آمنة ويعتمد عليها تماماً.
This machine over here
هذه الآلة هنا
is actually two separate two-propeller flying machines.
هي في الحقيقة آلتان طائرتان منفصلتان كل منهما بمروحتين.
This one wants to spin clockwise.
هذه تريد الدوران مع عقارب الساعة.
This other one wants to spin counterclockwise.
وهذه الأخرى تريد الدوران عكس عقارب الساعة.
When you put them together,
و عندما نضعهما معاً،
they behave like one high-performance quadrocopter.
ستتصرفان و كأنهما مروحية رباعية واحدة ذات أداء عالي.
If anything goes wrong, however --
لكن في حال حدوث خلل ما --
a motor fails, a propeller fails, electronics, even a battery pack --
مثل عطل محرك أو مروحة أو حتى بطارية --
the machine can still fly, albeit in a degraded fashion.
ستبقى الآلة قادرة على الطيران، ولو بكفاءة أدنى .
We're going to demonstrate this to you now by disabling one of its halves.
و سنظهر لكم هذه الحالة الآن بتعطيل أحد نصفيها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This last demonstration
هذا العرض الأخير
is an exploration of synthetic swarms.
هو استكشاف الأسراب الاصطناعية.
The large number of autonomous, coordinated entities
إن العدد الكبير من الوحدات الحرة المتناسقة
offers a new palette for aesthetic expression.
يقدم لوحة من التعابير الجمالية.
We've taken commercially available micro quadcopters,
لقد أخذنا العدد المتوفرتجارياً من المروحيات الرباعية الصغيرة،
each weighing less than a slice of bread, by the way,
يزن كل منها أقل من شريحة خبز بالمناسبة،
and outfitted them with our localization technology
وجهزناها بتقنياتنا المحددة للموقع
and custom algorithms.
و بالخوارزميات المناسبة.
Because each unit knows where it is in space
ولأن كل واحدة منها تعرف موقعها في الفضاء
and is self-controlled,
و تسيطر ذاتياً على نفسها،
there is really no limit to their number.
وهي بالحقيقة غير محدودة العدد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Hopefully, these demonstrations will motivate you to dream up
آمل أن هذه العروض ستدفعكم لتحلموا
new revolutionary roles for flying machines.
بأدوار ثورية مهمة للآلات الطائرة.
That ultrasafe one over there for example
تلك الأكثر أمانا هناك، على سبيل المثال
has aspirations to become a flying lampshade on Broadway.
لها تطلعات في أن تصبح ضوء إنارة طائر في برودواي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The reality is that it is difficult to predict
الحقيقة أنه يصعب التنبؤ
the impact of nascent technology.
بتأثيرهذه التقنية الوليدة.
And for folks like us, the real reward is the journey and the act of creation.
و لأفراد مثلنا، فإن مكافأتنا الحقيقية هي المسيرة والابتكار.
It's a continual reminder
و هي تذكير مستمر
of how wonderful and magical the universe we live in is,
بروعة و سحر الكون الذي نعيش فيه،
that it allows creative, clever creatures
الذي يسمح لمخلوقات ذكية و خلاقة
to sculpt it in such spectacular ways.
لنحته بهذه الطرق المذهلة .
The fact that this technology
الحقيقة أن هذه التكنولوجيا
has such huge commercial and economic potential
لها هذه القدرة التجارية والاقتصادية الهائلة
is just icing on the cake.
هي فقط زينة للكعكة.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)